Hi there, this is Geshe
Michael Roach and welcome to this
little talk about the practice
of The Thousand Angels
of the Heaven of Bliss.
I know you guys have
about another week or two
before you're going to go into
your 3-day weekend retreat.
I know that you'll be using
the practice of The Thousand Angels
in your 3-day retreat
and I just wanted to talk about it.
We've been through the
steps of it many times
and we'll talk a little
bit about that today.
I think I was trying to remember
the first time I ever
did this practice myself,
and the time that my
teacher taught it to me.
I remember it was a little bit,
it felt a little bit strange
because it was some Tibetan guy
and I was supposed to
close my eyes and
picture this Tibetan guy.
Of course my teacher had many paintings
of this ceremony,
there's Je Tsongkapa
up in on some clouds
and then out of,
he's coming out as the heart of Maitreya,
and then I'm supposed to
think about this Tibetan guy
and imagine that he's coming down.
Then I do all these nice things for him
and it was very foreign to me.
I didn't feel close to the
people that they were describing.
I didn't know Tibetans very well
and recently,
I was working on a text
about emptiness meditations,
and somebody asked me,
Veronica, my wife asked me,
"Well, where did Tibetan come from?"
You know you're always
talking about Sanskrit
and how it's says,
how we can get English
words out of Sanskrit.
Then she said, "I'm just curious about
where did the Tibetan come from?"
And I have to say,
I've heard people say it
just dropped out of the sky
and Tibetans will tell
you something like that,
that it just dropped out of the sky.
And then you read, if you go online,
you'll see people say oh,
it's Burmese, Tibeto-Burmese
language group but that
doesn't really help.
It just spread a little
bit in towards Burma.
It really does seem that had
just dropped out of the sky.
Linguistically, it's
not related to anything
in the world that I know of.
It really does seem like
it's from another planet.
I spent the last two days in a hospital,
a friend of mine is
undergoing some difficulties.
A couple of friends of mine
have got some serious illnesses
and they've asked me to help them.
And it got me thinking about
this world
and these are people who are close to me.
And one of them is not close to me,
but they heard about me and they asked,
they keep writing me
letters, emails, about
what's going to happen to them.
Then I was thinking about it myself
and how to explain it to them.
And I think at a certain age,
if you spend a lot of time
around people who are dying,
who are seriously ill,
and they trust you and
they're asking you for advice
and they're like, what's
going to happen to me
and what's it going to be like?
I think only when you have someone
talk to you, your phone
just did a clunky thing.
(indistinct chatter)
(Geshe-la laughing)
Yeah, that's from another world too.
Then,
something happened to
me in the last few days
and that I just became really
aware of different realms.
I've been trying to explain to someone
what's going to happen
to them when they die.
When you think about
someone leaving this world,
then this world becomes, I don't know,
in my mind it becomes like a pocket,
or some kind of a pocket,
and there's other worlds,
other pockets around it,
and there's little,
almost like submarine
hatches between the pockets.
Then you die in this pocket
and then you're going to go
through one of those hatches
to a different pocket that we can't see.
Then I don't know if
I'll ever see you again
anytime soon
because there's probably
millions of pockets like that
and you're going to go through
a small hatch or doorway
and you're going to pass
to a different pocket,
a different reality,
and we may not see each other again.
Like there's no reason to
think there's just one world,
there are many, many worlds,
and they may touch each
other like eggs in a carton
but they're completely
separate and they're different.
And you will go to a different world
and there will be different things there,
and different people there.
It may be completely different
from the world you're in now
and you can go there any time.
One of the people who's been writing me,
who is not a Buddhist,
and they're not interested in Buddhism,
but they are dying.
They found out about
me through a relative.
They were a strong, a healthy, young,
successful filmmaker, very famous,
in his field
and then just suddenly he's
got some kind of terrible
stomach cancer and they say,
he'll die in a few months.
And he just, he has a beautiful
son and a beautiful wife
and they're both filmmakers.
He's asking me what's going to happen?
Where am I going to go?
And it's kind of,
it's kind of interesting that he,
I don't know, for some reason
he thinks I can tell him.
Then he's really being
good about listening to me.
So it's kind of,
sometimes I've had that in my life where
someone will come to me and say,
I have a terrible disease
and only have a few weeks
and can you help me?
They're almost the best
students, right JB?
Beause they really listen
and they really do what you tell them.
So I'm trying to get you in the mood of,
somehow these Tibetan things came to us
and even as a language,
it seems that they dropped
out of another world.
Like all of these teachings
that we have in Tibetan language
just dropped out of another world,
and that John Brady and his team,
I mean, today, they're working on grants.
I'm trying to push them to
break into another library
in Mongolia that has 300,000 books there.
And it's just like, I can't stand it
to think that those books are there
and they might burn up tomorrow
or like something might happen.
It just drives me crazy,
like, wow, we have to
try to get those books.
Then I think about those books
and they also seem to
be from another world.
It just seems like they're
not from this normal world.
They're unique. Those
books are very unique.
So why am I talking about that?
The practice of The Thousand Angels,
it's kind of like you're trying
to open up a little doorway
to another world.
I have to say something about Tibetans
that maybe you don't know.
I've lived with Tibetans for 25 years
and I was surprised about some things:
One is that
as a country,
they're are not different
from any other country. Okay?
I'm sorry to say that
but there's no big
difference between Tibet,
and America, and Russia, and India,
and China. There's not a big difference.
The country as a country
is not much different.
I was very, what do you call it?,
kind of disappointed. I was disappointed
when I got to know normal Tibetan people.
I started talking with them
and seeing how they live,
and they're just about
like everybody else.
There's good people.
There's really bad people.
There's greedy people.
There were wars.
There was terrible
killing and hurting people.
And it's not different
from Europe or America,
or it's not different, the
people are basically the same.
But they have this one doorway
to another world
and I don't know why, it
just came through Tibet.
So, I mean, if you ever have
to live in Tibetan society
and deal closely with
Tibetan, even in a monastery,
it's disappointing.
They're just pretty normal
and they have the same kind of
very sad things going on there
that go on every place else.
But there's this one doorway that
they learned how to open and that's,
to me, we're talking about Tsongkapa.
So, I mean, even the name Tsongkapa
when I started to learn about Tsongkapa,
it was very uncomfortable.
I'm like,
and they can't even agree
how to spell it right, John?
Everyone wants to spell
it a different way.
I mean, nobody's name
starts with TZ anywhere.
It's just weird, and it's hard
to remember when you're new
to remember that name
and why didn't they call
him John or something easy?
It's just Tsongkapa.
It felt strange and foreign
to me when I first learned it.
It felt kind of
distant like I would never be able to,
I couldn't see that I felt
too close to this person
and I didn't feel that attracted to them.
My teacher was insisting
that I should try to
learn about Tsongkapa,
and study about Tsongkapa,
and read Tsongkapa's books,
and I should try to get
a personal relationship
with Tsongkapa,
which is what you're trying
to do in these three days.
You're trying to get a
personal relationship
with Tsongkapa. I just want to say,
I don't know where you're from,
Russia, China, wherever you're from,
Mexico, but it's weird there's
somebody named Tsongkapa.
They wear strange clothes.
It's not something easy to relate to.
It's not something from our culture.
It's a totally different thing.
Then I struggled with that
and I'll be honest about it.
In the first few years that I spent
in this small Mongolian monastery,
I struggled with that and
I didn't feel very close to
Tsongkapa. It was very foreign
and I didn't know much about him.
All I heard was he wrote a lot of books
and there were complicated and difficult.
I wasn't attracted to it,
but the point of this practice is that--
I can tell a story of Tsongkapa.
And Tim, you got an image I think,
the first one, maybe.
Yeah, this is a nice story
I think the DCI people know it.
So Tsongkapa wanted to have a relationship
with Manjushri. And Manjushri, again,
that's some kind of foreign
word, and foreign name,
and foreign person,
and I remember trying to learn his name,
and all the Westerners in my
class already knew his name
and I didn't.
I felt uncomfortable
that they knew his name
and I didn't know his name
so they must know who he is
but I don't know who he is.
Everybody would say, oh, he's the
god of wisdom.
I'm like, well, what's the god of wisdom?
And so Tsongkapa is,
I think he's the person with
his hands like this [in prayer]
in the middle.
He wants to meet Manjushri.
So he heard that Manjushri
understands emptiness
and he really wants to meet him.
He's kind of not like you and me,
like Tsongkapa's not thinking,
oh, I would like to meet a teacher
who can explain about Manjushri to me.
He's not thinking like that.
He's thinking, well, if the
source from another world
about emptiness teachings is Manjushri
- -this is so Tsongkapa--
then I want to to meet him myself.
Just tell me where he lives
then I'll get in touch with him.
I don't need you guys to
tell me what Manjushri said.
So he goes around asking everybody.
I'm glad you're offering me
classes. I appreciate it.
I've learned a lot but
could I just talk to
Manjushri directly?
And then everybody says, well,
that takes the years of practice.
He says, well, is there
anybody who actually did it?
That's the kind of dumb,
smart question that new people will ask
and later when you get more
experienced, you stop asking.
But I think you should ask.
He said, well, can I
just meet him directly?
Then somebody said, well,
there is a guy who met
Manjushri. There is such a person.
Then he says, well,
just tell me his address
and I'll go talk to him.
They're like, he doesn't have an address.
He's like, what do you mean
doesn't have an address?
He's up on the Sedona mountain somewhere.
He's wandering around
with a bunch of sheep.
He doesn't have a house.
He just keeps sheep in the mountains.
If you go wander around the mountains,
you might run into him.
It's so funny, right?
Like just there's one
mountain, there's another one,
there's another. Good luck.
He says, well, okay, what's his name?
They say, Umapa,
which kind of means
Master of the Middle Way.
His name means kind of
Master of the Middle Way,
but he's a sheep herder.
So Tsongkapa's like, okay,
let me go try to find him.
And that picture, Tim, you got it?
They should've put it in a,
they should have put it in a
meadow on a mountain somewhere
but anyway, Tsongkapa meets Umapa,
and he says,
I heard that you got direct
contact with Manjushri
and I heard that you can
talk to him directly.
And Umapa says,
yeah, I just imagine he's like,
- yep, I got that,
because he's probably no teeth,
he's just a sheep herder
up in the mountains.
- -Yeah, yeah, yeah, I'm direct
contact, yeah, that's me.
And so Tsongkapa is like,
- -Do you mind if we just confirmed this?
Can you put the picture back?
This is the moment of confirmation.
Tsongkapa says,
look, I'll ask you
questions about emptiness
and then
you ask Manjushri what he thinks.
I'll ask you some
difficult questions I have
and then you talk to Manjushri
and then I'll judge from your answers
whether you're in contact
with Manjushri or not.
So we, unfortunately we
don't have the questions.
It would make a good movie.
So he starts asking questions
and then Umapa tarts answering.
And the answers are perfect.
The answers are totally perfect.
Then Tsongkapa was like,
oh my God, you really are
in contact with Manjushri.
Then of course,
he writes down all the answers.
He incorporates them into
some of his greatest books
on emptiness.
Then he gets kind of
impatient and he says, well,
how about I just talk
to Manjushri directly?
Can you introduce me to Manjushri?
Umapa says it doesn't work like that.
You don't have the karma.
You don't have the seeds to see Manjushri.
You can't just ask me to
introduce you to Manjushri,
it won't work.
He could be sitting next to
you; he is sitting next to you.
And you can't see him because
you don't have the seeds.
So it's not like
I can make an introduction,
you have to make the seeds.
You have to collect the seeds
to meet him and then
everything will be awesome.
Then you can, it'll really be awesome.
So I encourage you to make the seeds.
And he helped him to make the seeds.
The biggest seed of all
is to realize that it takes
seeds to meet Manjushri.
That's all.
The biggest seed to
meet Manjushri directly
is to understand emptiness enough
to understand that Manjushri
is coming from you.
So if you really want to meet Manjushri,
you can. You just have to plant the seeds.
The most powerful seed
is to believe you can.
BTAGS PA'I RNAL 'BYOR -- What's that mean?
$500.
(indistinct chatter)
Tim got it, $500.
Collect from Elly I think,
$500 for the young man.
BTAGS PA'I RNAL 'BJOR means,
it starts by believing
that it could happen.
You just kind of pretend
And Tsongkapa does it.
Why are we talking about that?
We're supposed to be talking about
the practice of The Thousand Angels
and trying to make contact with Tsongkapa.
Again, what I want to say is
that for me,
I'm stuck in this little
Mongolian temple in New Jersey
and here's these people
talking about this guy
whose name I can't pronounce.
And they're trying to prove to me
that this is going to save my life
and I never heard of him at Princeton.
And I'm like,
"Are you sure, you know?
Then Rinpoche taught me
the DGA' LDAN LHA BRGYA MA
The Thousand Angels Practice.
These are seven, eight steps that you do
before a meditation practice.
It's called BSAGS SBYANG
Say BSAGS SBYANG
And you guys know BSAGS SBYANG,
I think, BSAGS collect good, new karma.
The word TSOGS comes from BSAGS.
So when you do your TSOGS twice a month,
by assembling great
quantities of offerings,
which is called TSOGS, TSOGS-ing them,
that's called BSAGS.
Then SBYANG means like,
GSO SBYONG comes from SBYANG,
which means to confess your bad deeds.
So the whole practice
of The Thousand Angels
is to BSAGS SBYANG.
On one hand, you want to try to accumulate
a big pile of good seeds,
and then SBYANG means
you want to clean away
a big pile of bad seeds.
If you're do enough
collecting new seeds
and if you get rid of enough bad seeds,
then the door opens to another realm
and Tsongkapa shows up in your life,
personally in your life.
You see?
So the purpose of
this ritual is to make contact,
direct contact with Tsongkapa
the way he did with Manjushri.
So you're trying to
get the portal to open.
It's a lot easier if
you know how it works.
It's not that Tsongkapa's
waiting for you to ask politely,
or Tsongkapa refuses to
come to your meditation room
if you don't do The Thousand Angels
a thousand times at first,
and then on the thousandth
time, he'll come.
It's not like that.
It feels like that when you're new,
when you're just starting.
It feels like, okay, I'm going
to have to do 500 of these
or I'm going to have to do 600 of these,
and then maybe Tsongkapa will be happy
and come visit me, you know?
But it's not like that.
It's that you have to open the door
to get him to come
and you open the door by doing the ritual,
by repeating this ritual.
And I'll be honest,
I just did it out of respect
for my teacher. He said,
do this practice and I
was not attracted to it
and I didn't see much point to it.
I waited a long time
before I did my retreats
because I wasn't attracted to it.
I just thought it was
kind of superstitious
and I thought just
,DGA' LDAN LHA BRGYA'I
MGON GYI THUGS KA NAS,
,RAB DKAR ZHO GSAR SPUNGS
'DRA'I CHU 'DZIN RTZER,
,CHOS KYI RGYAL PO KUN
MKHYEN BLO BZANG GRAGS,
,SRAS DANG BCAS PA GNAS
'DIR GSHEGS SU GSOL,
I'll go, okay, I recited it 25 times
and nothing happened.
I just felt it was kind of artificial
but if you can get into
the actual practice,
then Tsongkapa does come
and he's cool.
So I know he has a strange name,
I think Je Rinpoche
might be easier, right?
This call him Je Rinpoche,
that's his other name,
which means precious one
or something like that.
But I just want to encourage you
to do the practice
because if you do it in a relaxed,
happy, creative way,
the door does open to another realm
and he comes,
and he starts talking in your head
and it's really cool.
So, you can meet those people
and he is amazing.
So let's talk about Tsongkapa.
We just finished, right?,
editing a book about him.
We wrote a book,
I don't know, 20 years ago.
We translated a book about his life
and we made a big thick, expensive book
as a fundraiser to help this
little Mongolian temple.
And we sold all the books finally
and I think it was a
hundred thousand dollars.
We gave all the money to the temple.
We saved some money to
print the book again.
Recently we were editing the book.
We're cleaning it up to make it into a,
now that we thought all the copies
to help the temple,
we were making paperback,
a big paperback book,
coffee table book, and
we'll be releasing it,
I think, on, on new year's party?
(indistinct chatter)
At the, Insha Allah,
at the new year's party in Singapore.
Let's talk about that book.
In the book,
you can read,
basically,
the biography of his life
is a story about writing books.
So here's this great master
and he did do other
things than write books.
He went into deep retreats
and there's a beautiful
painting of him in a KO BA,
KO BA means
a leather coracle in English.
It's a boat made of a
skin of a vaca, of a cow,
and it must be scary, I don't know.
They don't have bridges in Tibet
and they have the most rivers
of anywhere in the world,
the most streams.
You can't walk five miles
without crossing a couple of rivers.
So you jump in one of these
little personal boats.
It's round and then
somebody pushes you over
and then you get out and you keep going.
So there's a beautiful picture of him
and his eight closest disciples
going to YAR MO KLUNG, which is a place
that he did a retreat.
There's also a picture,
Tim, you got it there.
It's I think it's the
last picture you have.
And before he went to retreat,
he was having some physical problems.
And I think that's kind of encouraging
that Tsongkapa had physical problems.
He had bad back, he had a bad back.
His whole life he had a bad back
and it was hard for him to meditate,
and it was hard for him to do retreat.
Here he's meeting a yoga master,
and he's offering him a mandala.
I think that's very
important in your retreat.
When you do your three-day retreat
or a three-year retreat,
I've been having fun,
doing yoga with Connie,
the Director of Yoga Studies Institute,
and John Brday,
every day, we've been doing yoga together
and it's a great practice.
So if you're going to do
this three-day retreat,
I really encourage you,
do what Tsongkapa did
and take care of your health.
You got to have a physical body
to do The Thousand Angel practice.
And to make contact with Tsongkapa,
you have to have a healthy, physical body.
So you have to take good care of your body
and you only get one.
So it's a really important every day
to do some physical practices,
and to eat carefully,
and to get enough sleep,
that helps you open the door.
So you do see other,
a lot of other paintings
of Tsongkapa doing different things,
but the main thing was writing
books and studying books.
I want to tell you a story of a book
I'm working on right now.
So I'm in a group of
translators called Mixed Nuts
and we decided to try to translate
the most, maybe the twenty,
most important books
in the world from ancient Buddhism.
So I got like ten fools, including Seiji,
what do you call in Spanish?
Locos. Personas Locos.
And I said,
let's translate the twenty greatest books
of a Buddhism together,
and some of the Mixed Nuts
had no experience in
Tibet and translation.
Like Seiji, like zero,
he didn't know any words and I
said, well, let's just start.
So we've been working
really, really, really hard
for five years,
and there's about ten main translators
and they all have a very
difficult book to translate,
and they're all struggling.
I'm really amazed and grateful
that no one has quit yet.
So I don't know why.
I don't have a good record in the past.
Most of the people who learned
to translate with me quit,
but none of these ten people has quit,
which means intense amount of work for me,
like hundreds of hours of work.
Just the classes are,
just the classes and the
class preparation is,
I have five, six hundred hours of work
and it's intense.
Then people I know are asking me,
can you do this Geshe-la?
Can we have a meeting?
Can we just talk for ten minutes?
Can we go out and have coffee?
Can you come over to my house?
Someone told me recently they see,
they live in Sedona they said,
I see Stanley and Alison
more than I see you Geshe-la.
They live in China.
And I'm like, I'm sorry but it's intense,
the amount of work is intense.
And then the question is,
is it a good spiritual practice
to spend your whole day in books?
It seems like Tsongkapa's thing
that he was spending
most of his day in books
and not really meeting a
lot of other people, and not
socializing, and not getting
to see the people's real lives.
It seems almost artificial
to spend your whole day in books.
And it also seems
too technical.
It seems, Geshe-la, like
if that's what it takes
to meet Tsongkapa, if I have to read
those thousands of pages
that the Mixed Nuts are
spitting out, then it just
doesn't seem practical,
it seems like it's too scholarly.
So I wanted to say as a method
of reaching those other
worlds, it's fantastic.
I know it's not a popular thing to say
and I know those books
are difficult books.
They are difficult books. They
are really difficult books.
But I want to say it's our lineage,
in Tsongkapa's method,
to put your head in those
books a couple hours
a day and struggle. It's not easy.
It's not easy. It's difficult
and it's a hard. It's
just hard to sit there.
It's hard to read
hour after hour
things that you don't understand.
It's just frustrating,
and I don't know,
it's like trying to
read a foreign language
and you can't get it.
There's foreign languages
that you can't: French.
I decided three times to learn French
or Chinese,
and it's frustrating.
And it doesn't seem
very mystical and it
doesn't seem very sweet.
And rasa, it doesn't have much flavor.
But I want to describe what happens
and I think it happened to Tsongkapa
if you read his life story.
We are trying to invite
with the practice of The Thousand Angels,
we are trying to invite
to our meditation room
a person who spent many, many years
deep inside those ancient classics
that John Brady has been saving,
and because of that, he found a door,
he created a door to meet these beings
from another world.
And Tibet as a country,
as a, what do you call it?,
governmental structure,
it's lousy.
I mean, it's like below average.
I'm sorry, as a country,
it's kind of dysfunctional.
That's it not the point of
what's going on in Tibet.
The point is that there are people there
who worked on these ideas,
struggled through those great books,
day after day,
and the karma of that
was that they opened a window
to another world, you see?
People came from another world
and help them, and we can do it too.
So when you do the practice
of The Thousand Angels,
what's really happening is
you are trying to open a door
and then you will meet these
unbelievable people from another realm.
And they aren't,
they're not like us
and it's even uncomfortable
to be with them
because they're so good it's frustrating.
And you feel,
you feel like an idiot when
you're sitting with them.
So I really want to encourage you
to learn this practice.
I know it's very foreign.
I know it's not a language
that we're familiar with.
I know even the main guy's
name is hard to pronounce
but without being romantic,
and what do you call it?,
sentimental, you can open
a window to another world.
And those Himalayas, they were,
Shangri-La, they real a
doorway to another world.
Again, I'm not attracted to Tibetan
country as a country.
It's just another country.
It's not different from
any country you've been to.
But the doorway is there.
And if you practice The Thousand Angels,
you can open that doorway.
I'm not going to,
I personally,
I've taken you through those steps
in The Thousand Angels many times.
I kind of want to talk
about something else today.
You can do those on your own
and you don't need me to explain to you
which flower is blue
and which flower is red,
that you're going to be
offering. You can do that.
But I'd like to talk about an experience.
So I've been translating,
I've been helping prepare
a book by,
it's being translated by
Venerable Utpala, Bets Greer.
She's been working on this
book for about five years
and many of you have
been through the classes.
And it was hard.
The book was hard.
It's supposed to be
a book of emptiness meditations.
And we worked on it,
many of you guys came to the classes,
and we spend an hour,
we go about half a page.
We can't understand much.
I know the words, I can explain it to you.
But it's difficult. It's
really, really difficult.
And she finished, she finished her book.
Then I have to kind of
work on the translation,
make it smooth.
Sp I have a pleasant
duty that I have to go through
and make the whole translation.
I have to really
connect the five years of classes
into one beautiful flow and that's my job.
So I started
and then that starts blowing my mind.
I start seeing this pattern:
I taught the book to her for five years
and I didn't see the pattern.
Now I have to lay the whole thing out
and I'm like, oh my god.
It's 25 emptiness meditations
and they're stunning.
They're just stunning.
It's not one or two proofs of
emptiness, it's twenty five,
one after another. They're
deep. They're very, very deep.
And if you can't just,
if you don't spend time
with them, you don't get it.
One and Many: things are not one
and things are not more than one.
Things are not one and
things are not more than one.
Really. Why?
Because they have parts.
Things are not one,
nothing in the world is one thing
and nothing in the world
is more than one thing
because they have parts.
Everything has parts.
And then they go on like that.
It's a long, long,
oh my god, twenty five proofs.
And then there's another flow under it,
which is through the great four schools.
So sometimes you get the same argument
taught from a different school.
So he repeats the argument
of One and Many, three times,
but from different schools.
And then it's unbelievable.
It's just unbelievable
and then suddenly you're
like, oh my gosh, I get it.
I finally got it and then he says,
wait, let me tell you something else.
nd you're like, okay, I
got it, I got 25% emptiness
in my head and I understand it.
And I just used it with my wife.
That's the cool thing, right?
It's like, oh my god, I
got it in the morning,
I translated it, and in
the afternoon I used it
when she asked me why I didn't
do the laundry or something.
I actually took one of
those proofs of emptiness
and I secretly used it,
and I opened a portal to
another world by using it,
and I was, so wow.
I was like, wow, that's cool.
Oh, you have parts.
Your laundry has parts.
And she's like, huh?
I got it. Oh! You know, and then
the author, who is called Chone Lama,
he lived
250 years after Tsongkapa,
but I think he was Tsongkapa.
I think he was Tsongkapa.
A lot of the books
we are transcending, Seiji knows,
there are from Chone Lama,
and he's like Tsongkapa
but more accessible and
he's more reachable.
And so he says, hey,
you liked the twenty five?
Worked with the laundry, huh?
Like you get to know these guys,
you're like,
- -Hey it worked with the
laundry and your wife, right?
I say, Yeah, yeah, it was,
it didn't just work,
it was like opening a
door to another world
in the washroom.
Then he's like, Well, let
me show you something else.
Then he goes through fifteen proofs of,
fifteen mistaken proofs of emptiness,
slightly defective emptiness
proofs and that's so cool.
He says, Hey, I got a proof for you,
how about this one?
And then you go, you
read it and then he says,
- - How do you like that one?
And you're like,
- - Sounds great to me, and he says,
- - Nah, it's messed up.
And you're like, Why is it messed up?
And he says, Well, look
at this little thing here,
it doesn't work.
And you're like, Yeah,
I never thought of that,
that doesn't work does it?
So after he teaches you twenty five,
is it twenty three correct
proofs of emptiness,
from all four and a half
schools of ancient Buddhism,
then he says, hHy, let's
do some messed up proofs,
let's go through some messed up proofs.
I'll mess something up and
you tell me what's messed up.
And then you're like, I
don't see anything messed up
and then he takes you through fifteen
different messed up proofs to emptiness
that you've probably said
to your friends many times.
It's just awesome.
Then you're like, Oh man I'm so happy
and I'm almost at the end of the book,
and I can send it off
Elly to get it printed.
Everyone's going to be so happy.
And then he, at the end
of the book, he says,
I forgot to tell you how to
meditate on the emptiness.
And you're like, How he going
to do that with 2 pages left?
How's he going to teach you
how to meditate with two pages left?
And then he says, Well,
I don't really have space
in the book anymore to tell
you how to meditate on it.
I'll tell you there's three
steps to the meditation.
First you have to learn the book.
You must get a hold of an emptiness book
and you must spend time
with a qualified teacher and read it.
And you have to
struggle with those ideas.
You have to struggle.
Learn the correct ones.
Learn the wrong ones.
Struggle why this is
correct, this is wrong.
Struggle with why
this school explains
the same proof different
from that school.
Struggle with those things.
That's called Sruthi, right?
Learning in the class, classroom hours.
And then I wanted to go to BSAM PA, right?
What is that?
%Cintaya or something.
I want you to contemplate
what you learned.
For me, that's when I'm driving.
I don't know, when driving,
Veronica swears by it.
She says driving is my meditation time.
It's actually a contemplation time.
If you meditate, you'll crash.
So she's like, she mulls things over
and she thinks things over in the car,
and it's a really sweet practice.
So you're like, well,
so I'm having trouble
with this jewelry thing.
Let's see, does it have parts?
Is it empty? And you do that in the car
and then you get to
that and, then he says,
then you can get to,
then you can meditate on
what you contemplated on
when you get home in the car,
then get out of the car
and take 20 minutes on your cushion,
and go into it deep and see if
you can see it in meditation,
what you learned in the car
that you learned from the book.
Then he stops the book.
Chone Lama stops the book.
So I was frustrated and I said,
This is kind of dumb.
We're going to call this
book, emptiness meditations
and there's 38 proofs of emptiness
and there's three
sentences about meditation?
Then, you know, that's
not going to go over well.
Let's add the meditation
section from Pabongka Rinpoche
to the second half of the book.
Let's add it to the book so then you get
in the first half of the
book, like 200 pages,
you get emptiness proofs,
and then you get 200
pages of how to meditate,
all the details of how to meditate.
And I said, oh wow,
that's what we'll do.
We'll add Pabongka Rinpoche's
explanation cause it's really,
it's also,
I've taught it so many times
that I could translate
with my eyes closed.
And I said, Ah, just knock that out.
And so,
that's going to be 200 more pages.
And then I thought, well,
he based his meditation
description on
on Kamalashila's
Stages of Meditation and
there's a beautiful chart,
there's a beautiful carving
of all the stages of meditation.
They kept it in the...I
shouldn't say it....
Anyway, I ran into this chart once
and I copied it. I mean,
I took photographs of it
and I learned what it
meant. I translated it.
I learned to read it.
And so I said, well, let's
put the chart in the book
and that will be beautiful for people,
and I'll translate the whole chart.
So we did, we got the whole chart
and we put it in the book.
And then I was like, Well, this chart
comes from Kamalashila
and it's interesting cause he's an Indian
who was a great meditator
and a great emptiness master,
and a great Mind-Only master.
You guys read his commentary,
we went through his commentary
on the Diamond Cutter Sutra.
He actually went to Tibet
and he had some interesting
debates with people
and stuff like that. So he was passionate
about teaching people meditation.
Then he wrote three famous books
as John knows, he went
and got them for me,
called "The Stages of Meditation".
They kind of overlap. You can tell
they might be manuals
that he prepared for DCI,
SCIM, and ACI.
And so it's the same stuff
in a different package.
Then there's a fourth one,
a very beautiful one that he wrote.
So I was looking at those
and I was trying to choose
which one to translate.
Then I noticed there's another
stages of the meditation
in the Tengyur from ancient India.
This is, I said, oh, I
wonder who wrote that?
Nagarjuna.
Arya Nagarjuna I said, Oh my god,
there's another book on how to meditate,
written by the greatest
emptiness master of all time?
Wow, let's go look at that.
It's got the same name as
Kamalashila's three books.
It's the same name.
So I'm like, Wow,
I wonder if Kamalashila ripped this off
from Nagarjuna,
and the way I'm ripping the
mine off of Kamalashila,
and the way Pabonka and me ripped off it.
So I went and read that one
and it's a stunning book about
the stages of meditation,
heavily mixed with emptiness teachings,
heavy, heavy emptiness
teachings and how to meditate.
So you got this thing, you see,
you could learn the posture of retreat,
learn everything about how to meditate
from Pabongka Rinpoche
Then use the chart.
Put the chart in your meditation room,
and use that every day to
work on your meditation.
And then go through
Kamalashila's meditation book
and then go through Nagarjuna's
book, with the same name,
but deeper on the emptiness part,
and then slide into Chone
Lama's 38 proofs the emptiness,
which is really just Tsongkapa recooked.
You see what I mean?
So you get this whole
picture of a huge work:
half vipashayana, half shamatha,
first half how to see emptiness,
second half how to get into
meditation to see emptiness.
So now you've got 200 pages
on vipashayana, how to see emptiness,
and then you got 200 pages
on how to meditate, shamatha.
So really it's this now, poor Bets' book,
has become this great, incredible
book. It's a real
emptiness meditation book.
So half of it is how
to understand emptiness
and then half of it is how to meditate,
which is the great marriage
of vipashayana and shamatha.
Vipashayana: insight into emptiness
Shamatha: quiet, quietude,
getting silent, silence.
Silence and insight matched
together in one book.
Guess who did that before?
Tsongkapa's in a retreat
and he's like, God, we should make a book
that's 50% vipashayana and 50% shamatha.
And he writes like,
it would be about a
thousand pages in English
and he just knocks it out.
And then, I don't know, Manjrushi is like,
Hey why don't you do the
first four perfections,
throw it in there.
Let's call it Lam Rim.
So he's got emptiness teaching,
shamatha, joined together
and then Manjrushi says,
Ah, tack on this Lam Rim
stuff at the beginning.
And so,
that's what Tsongkapa did,
So that's what Tsongkapa was up to.
Why am I talking about that?
Well, first of all, I'm
obsessed with it nowadays.
But secondly,
use it when you do your
Thousand Angels practice.
Try to understand
that you are going to be doing,
let's go through it okay?
PHYAG 'TSAL BA DANG
MCHOD CING BSHAGS PA DANG
RJES SU YI RANG
These are the seven steps, right?
First one, PHYAG 'TSAL BA
Bow down to...How much time I got left?
Okay, yeah, we got time.
So the basic structure
of The Thousand Angels practice,
which I would like it to
do with a special mantra,
called OM MANI PADME HUNG,
and I'll explain more about that.
First thing, how to get this guy
to come through the doorway
from the other realm.
There's a certain etiquette.
In the New Testament, the Bible,
Jesus always washes his
disciples feet when they show up,
which is very unusual for the master
and we kind of got to do the same thing.
It's like cookies for
Santa Claus under the tree.
I don't know about you, but my
family was very serious about
Christmas cookies for Santa Claus.
One night I went out to see Santa Claus
and I saw my dad eating them.
But anyway,
first thing, prostrate to Tsongkapa.
Now I feel uncomfortable prostrating.
I did grow up Christian
and one of the rules in Christianity
is not to bow down to, I don't know,
unapproved objects.
So I always felt uncomfortable
to do prostration
but really the first step of
the DGA' LDAN LHA BRGYA MA
is just to admire Tsongkapa
and that's a prostration
and that's all.
If you want to get some
exercise, then prostrate.
But the real prostration
is just to admire this guy.
The real way to get him
to come through the portal
and show up in your meditation
room, which is possible,
that's what I'm trying to say today.
It is possible, you can get him there,
and it's awesome.
First thing you have to
say, "god, you're so cool."
You're just so cool.
All the stuff you did,
mainly that you taught us emptiness
and how to meditate.
You brought that into this
world from your world,
that was cool.
So if you just admire him,
you did the first one.
PHYAG 'TSAL BA DANG
MCHOD means MCHOD PA,
Yeah make some kind of offerings.
I know it's a tradition
to offer water cups,
and fruit, and stuff like that.
I was never much into it. I'll be honest.
I did it.
I can make a TGOR MA as good as anybody.
But what Tsongkapa really wants from you
is an offering of your goodness.
So he wants to hear that you
called somebody in the hospital
or that you wash the dishes
at the building after everybody else left,
right Nour?
The other roaches were running around.
That's the kind of offering
that Tsongkapa really wants.
My neighbor was pissing me off
and I went out and talked to him,
and asked him about his family,
and I admired his new truck
with the decals on the back.
And you know, that's a
great truck. I did it, okay?
And that's the kind of thing.
That's the offering Tsongkapa wants.
It's okay if you're meditating
and you're in a three day retreat.
Okay, get some fruits,
and donuts, and stuff,
and make offerings.
That's fine. That's good.
My teacher would spend two or three hours
at the grocery store checking
every kind of cookie,
the whole aisle,
and then he would decide on one
and then he would carefully
stand there for half an hour
and look through the plastic
and try to see if any of them were chipped
because it's improper to
offer a chipped cookie
to Tsongkapa.
So they should be perfect, that's fine.
But also don't forget that what Tsongkapa
really likes for offerings is some small,
saying you did like wash the dishes
at the college building
after everybody else dumped them on you
and went home,
and you're trying to hold a baby
and wash them with one hand.
It's like, that's good yoga.
You don't have to have barbells.
PHYAG 'TSAL BA DANG MCHOD CING BSHAGS PA
Then confess mistakes you've made.
If you think you haven't
made any mistakes,
that proves you're not meditating
because you make mistakes all day
and you repeat mistakes your whole life.
I'm 60 something years old
and I can tell you, 68,
you repeat the same mistakes every year,
over and over again.
If you can't think of any
mistakes to tell Tsongkapa
then you've reached the
real mindless meditation.
So, tell the stuff you've done
that you're not proud
of and get it out away.
He enjoys talking to people
who will admit that they made mistakes.
If you're the kind of person
who wants to pretend,
you're perfect, okay.
But when you die, it's going to be messy.
So just be honest about who you really are
and tell Tsongkapa all your mistakes.
Normally we tell everybody
our second worst mistake
and we hide our first worst mistake,
but with Tsongkapa, you can
tell them the worst one.
PHYAG 'TSAL BA DANG
MCHOD CING BSHAGS PA DANG
RJES SU YI RANG
What's that? YI RANG
Rejoice, be happy about other...
There's so much good in the world.
There are news outlets that talk about
the great things people do.
You got to work hard to find them.
They're not very well known.
They're not very popular
but there are news
channels on the internet
that honestly report,
not grand good deeds by people
but just normal people
who are cooking food for homeless people,
or doing nice things for people
and you got to work
hard to find these news.
The big news outlets are
only interested in scandals,
and troubles, and wars
and it's very unbalanced.
There's millions of people
doing kind things the whole day.
So enjoy.
Find one of those news outlets.
I get this stupid magazine
from my university
where they brag about all the
students and the professors.
And it's so nice to read.
Oh, this one just found out
how the virus grows this bump on it,
and how to take it off,
and stop the virus. And this guy just,
this secretary, who's been in
the McLean house at Princeton
for 34 years just passed away,
and she made coffee for
people every single day.
And these nice little things,
so rejoice in the things
that other people are doing.
RJES SU YI RANG
Then?
BSKUL ZHING
That's later.
What happens after that?
Request?
Yeah ask him to teach.
Ask him to teach you.
And it doesn't mean
Tsongkapa is going to
pop through his portal
and start talking to you.
He's probably going to send
you have a Mixed Nuts book
and say, I hope you open it.
I've been teaching a lot online.
I've been teaching some deep, deep books
and I have some students who prefer that,
and they are very brave
and they are unusual.
And I say, can I teach you
something that's not easy
and that you probably won't understand?
And they're like, "Yeah,
go ahead, Geshe-la".
And then I'm like, "Listen,
when you study things,
"when you try to read
things you can't understand,
"that affects you more
than listening to things
"that are comfortable for you."
Things that are uncomfortable to hear
because you don't understand them
have a very powerful effect on your mind.
Then things you know and
things you're familiar with,
to hear them again, is not very helpful.
So I have a small group of students,
I'll say, can I just teach you something
that you're not going to
understand for three years?
And they're like, yeah, go ahead Geshe-la.
They really work hard and
they don't understand it.
But they try and when you try,
it changes your brain.
It changes the
intelligence of you, spiritual
intelligence, it changes it.
But just keep doing the same
thing you always heard of,
that doesn't change much.
So struggling mentally with new ideas
is extremely
powerful on your mind.
Okay, I'm just saying,
try it for six months or so.
Read stuff you have no idea what it means
and just struggle, struggle, struggle.
And that's going to
change your entire being
much more than reading something
that you already familiar with.
So anyway, you're asking for teaching.
Don't forget the most powerful
thing when you ask for
teaching, they might send
trouble people who teach you stuff.
People who hurt you teach you more
than people who help you.
I'm sorry, that's the way it is.
So, when you ask for teaching,
watch out what you ask for
because you might get a whole pile of
irritating people showing up.
And that's a blessing.
I know you don't believe it but it's true.
When you have to struggle with somebody,
you advance. You become more advanced.
If you're just comfortable
with people you know,
you don't change much.
All right, what's the next one?
Yeah, ask them to stay.
And I have people all the time,
it's, "oh please stay."
And I'm like, yeah, I hope I can.
And I also would like to stay.
But it's a terrible tragedy
to come close to wisdom and lose it.
That's a real tragedy to come close to,
to come close to being
able to do a great retreat
and then lose it is a terrible,
I don't think there's anything
more tragic than that.
I talked to this famous movie maker
who has been writing,
he's been emailing me.
I never met him
in person. I never met him in person
and he just got cancer.
And he said, well,
okay, I'll do the chemo.
And they said, don't bother.
And he's like, what?
Can I do anything?
And they said, go home and die.
Don't take up space in the hospital.
Your wife can keep you as
comfortable as possible.
Here's Brompton's cocktail,
you know what this is?
It's what do you call that stuff?
(indistinct chatter)
It's like heroin.
It's like straight heroin.
They said here, when it gets bad,
when it gets into your bones, take this.
And then you'll die.
Say anything you want
to say to your family
because you won't be
able to talk after that.
You'll just be a vegetable,
but at least you'll be alive.
And so, it happens, things change.
You lose opportunities.
While you have a chance
to do a three-day retreat,
for God's sake, do a good one.
Take the time. Take the chance. Do it.
And do that retreat.
What's the last one?
Yeah dedicate the good karma,
like give it away to people.
I can't avoid
the image in my mind of a fire offering.
When we do fire offerings,
like at Diamond Mountain,
when the smoke goes out to the sky
and the wind blows it away,
I always imagine that sooner or later
it will touch everyone.
That mini pollution will sooner or later,
the particles of the offerings
during the fire offering
will reach all beings and do some kind of
imagine the good karma
being sent out like that.
And that's all.
What I'm saying it's hard
work, especially studying,
oh, one more thing.
Kamalashila, in the Stages of Meditation,
he rushes through
the actual stages, the
nine levels of meditation
and the five antidotes,
the eight,
the eight antidotes and the five problems.
He rushes through that.
I was like waiting for him,
I thought he would, his
book's kind of long.
So I thought, wow, he's
going to give some detail.
He doesn't. He rushes
through all the stuff
that's on the chart.
and then he spends like 20 pages on
SO SOR RNAM PAR RTOG PA
which means,
cogitating, in English.
Cogitating means to sit
in your meditation cabin.
Right, Connie?
For three years, three
months and three days
And just think about stuff.
Just thinking about why stuff empty
and don't forget
Kamalashila went to Tibet.
He and his teacher were involved
with these intense debates
with other practitioners
about the usefulness of
thinking about nothing.
There was even some intrigue.
Somebody was murdered.
And it got hot and don't
forget he was in this,
he was there
and so he spends about
200 pages in English,
defending thinking about emptiness.
He spends about 200 pages defending
trying to figure out
emptiness from the books.
He says, you have to. He
says it's not a luxury
and it's not some scholarly thing.
And it's not boring
and it's not difficult,
and it's not technical.
It's the only way to
see emptiness directly.
He goes on for,
in English it would be,
I dunno, almost 200 pages in English.
He's just keep repeating the same thing
over and over again.
You have to struggle
in meditation
to understand about emptiness.
Then it will turn into
the direct perception,
that will turn into the direct perception.
You got to get all this Mixed Nuts books.
You got to struggle through them.
You got to try and understand
the 38 proofs of emptiness.
You must do that struggle
and he says, without that,
forget it.
Then the last thing he says,
okay and then we can stop.
He says, you know when in Boy Scouts
or when they teach you
to rub sticks together
and make a fire, God, you don't
know how many days we spent
trying to do that in Boy Scouts.
It is possible but it's difficult.
You can do it with a bow and a string
and a bowl,
and certain kinds of
shavings from certain plants.
You can do it. I've done it
but it takes about four
hours or something.
A match is much easier.
We always had matches
hidden in our pockets.
Then he says, I tell you something,
struggle, struggle, struggle for hours
with these stupid two sticks,
and then he says, you
know it's really fun is
to throw the stick in
the fire first thing.
Once you get the fire
going, throw the stick in.
Then he's like, okay, see you guys later.
Then we're like, what?
Yeah, got it.
Well, yeah, yeah,
You use the stick, blah,
blah, blah, make the fire
and then throw the goddamn
stick in a fire and burn it up.
What he means is
there is a state of non-conceptual,
direct perception of emptiness
but the way you get there
is through thousands of
hours of conceptual thinking.
It's like the stick that makes the fire.
Then okay you can throw
the stick in the fire
and it will burn up,
in the fire of direct
perception of emptiness.
But you can't make it without the stick.
You can't make that
fire without the stick.
It's a very beautiful image.
It's a very, very beautiful image.
And by the way, that's where he says,
he says in Sanskrit,
I think it's DVAYAM or something.
%DVAYAM BHUMI ASHWA PASHYET DUAVAT - $1000
No, I'm not serious.
Show the horse the course
before you run the race.
It comes from him, I didn't know that.
You don't take a horse out for a race
without showing them the track first,
riding around the track
for a couple of days
and then you go on the race.
So it's like read the books on emptiness,
study them deeply, and then run your race.
Now what's the,
what are we doing with
the OM MANI PADME HUNG?
It's very simple.
I also used to,
okay, this is the whole stories
of things I didn't
believe from my teacher.
He said, I'll do this
mantra a thousand times,
or I'll do it 10,000 times
or do it 100,000 times.
Lock yourself in a room
and do this mantra.
And I was like,
yeah, okay, I'll get to that.
That was my thing with my teacher.
I learned that you're
not supposed to say no.
You just can delay.
I'll say, oh yeah,
as soon as I get some
couple of weeks off of work,
I definitely lock myself in a room
and say OM MANI PADME HUNGs.
It's on my list of things to do,
bucket list before I die.
Then he went on a trip to Europe
to see Jampel Sangye was
his name, %Tuchi's teacher,
he went to go see him in Rome.
So I was kind of stuck in the house alone
and I said, well, he's
got this guest room.
And I had another monk with
me and he said, I'll cook
if you want to say mantras.
So I said, yeah.
So I went in Rinpoche's guest room,
which I built,
and I did a two, three week retreat
and I just did OM MANI PADME HUNGs.
It's a very, very powerful mantra
and I don't think a lot of people
understand the meaning of the mantra.
But OM is called %SGO 'BYED
which means the door
that opens to the mantra.
So OM is the door of the mantra
and then HUNG at the end is, %GZER BTZUGS
which means to stick the sacred dagger
in the ground and say, "May
it be so." HUNG means that.
So OM is like, I'm about to say a mantra
and then HUNG is like, goddamn.
So between that, it's just MANI PADME
and MANI means a gem, gemstone,
a jewel.
It's funny because it sounds like money,
which you need to buy a jewel
Then PADMA means a Lotus flower
It's very important that it's PADME.
which John will tell you is
the, which case? The locative.
Yeah, in the lotus.
The jewel in the lotus.
So it's not just jewel lotus.
It's jewel in the lotus
And it's a reference to tantra.
It's a direct reference to tantra.
Tt's funny that it's a mantra.
If you're the kind of person
who believes it's possible
that your spiritual
partner could be a Buddha,
then it's very important to you.
And the people who criticize that
are doing OM MANI PADME
HUNG all day. It's so funny
because it means have a spiritual partner.
It's so funny that
the people who criticize the practice
of a spiritual partner, which
Buddha followed and taught,
say, Well, let's go do OM
MANI PADME HUNGs instead.
But OM MANI PADME HUNG means
I hope I meet my partner.
And it's funny. It just,
to me, it's funny.
But anyway.
So you can think of that jewel
as love and bodhichitta.
And you can think of the PADME
as inserting it into
understanding of emptiness.
So if you can, I like
to call it a marriage
of emptiness and compassion,
or a marriage of emptiness
and love for other people.
Then that's perfection
And that's Buddhahood.
So try to put your
compassion into emptiness
and that's OM MANI PADME HUNG.
So if you understand a little
bit about it and you do,
I would try to do 10,000.
Sometimes you can try to do 100,000.
Itt's not stupid to count
them. That's another myth.
It's very cool to count them.
And it's cool to reach 10,000.
And it's cool to reach 100,000.
And things happen at 10,000
that don't happen at
9,999. I'm telling you.
So set yourself a goal and get a rosary,
and try to do and keep track.
I keep hash mark: one, two,
three, [four] and then cross.
Five. Five hundred like that.
So keep it, actually keep a count
of how many do.
And it works. It really does work.
Trust me, I thought it was stupid
and I thought it was a waste of time,
and I thought it was
superstitious. And it's not.
It's a very, very powerful
and very beautiful.
So try to do three days of mantras.
You're supposed to not rush them.
You're supposed to say them
clearly or it doesn't work.
It doesn't work as well.
So don't rush them so
fast that you're like,
but (speaks too fast to
understand anything).
Try to use the third
finger of your left hand
and that has a special prana.
And it's more powerful.
It's uncomfortable for the first few days
but hold your rosary here.
okay, last story, grandpa's last story.
I was in a train station in India
and I was with a couple of hippie friends
and we didn't know anything.
We saw these Tibetans rushing
in to a little side room
and we're like, hey,
what's going on in there?
And they said, Ling Rinpoche is there,
the senior tutor. He's sitting in there.
And I'm like, wow, that's cool, man.
Can we meet him?
And they said, well, you can try.
And they said, normally you
got to have an offering.
So we run across the street,
we bought this crummy
little cake at a bake shop.
We rushed back to the waiting room
and he's in there, and the train's coming
and we said we got the cake.
We can come in?
Then I can go in and we met him.
We had an extraordinary meeting
but he was going like this the whole time
and he didn't have rosary.
He did so many mantras that
he decided he didn't
need the rosary anymore.
So he would just be like this all day
It was kind of a weird thing
we're like, what's going on with his hand?
And they are like, he's doing mantras.
I said does he need a rosary?
I could go buy one.
They said, nah he doesn't
even want anymore.
So do your mantras and enjoy.
And work hard.
When you work hard,
when you study things you don't
understand, you learn more.
When you study things, you do understand,
you don't learn as much.
Okay, all right see you guys later.
Good luck on your retreat. Thank you.